Hidden by darkness. Guarded by witches. Discovered by a boy. Stolen by a
king. Whoever owns it will rule the world. Or destroy it.
The Black Cauldron is a animation, adventure,
family film directed by Ted Berman.
Taran is an assistant pigkeeper with boyish dreams of becoming a great warrior.
However, he has to put the daydreaming aside when his charge, an oracular pig
named Hen Wen, is kidnapped by an evil lord known as the Horned King.
The villain hopes Hen will show him the way to The Black Cauldron, which has
the power to create a giant army of unstoppable soldiers.
Taran (voice), played by Grant Bardsley.
Eilonwy (voice), played by Susan Sheridan.
Gurgi / Doli (voice), played by John Byner.
Fflewddur Fflam (voice), played by Nigel Hawthorne.
The Horned King (voice), played by John Hurt.
Dallben (voice), played by Freddie Jones.
The Black Cauldron is a 1985 American animated dark fantasy
adventure film produced by Walt Disney Feature Animation.
It is loosely based on the first two books in The Chronicles of Prydain
series of novels, which are in turn based on Welsh mythology.
The film was directed by Ted Berman and Richard Rich, and features the ensemble voice cast of Grant Bardsley, Susan Sheridan, Freddie Jones,
Nigel Hawthorne, Arthur Malet, John Byner, Phil Fondacaro, and John Hurt, with John Huston serving as the narrator for the prologue.
Set in the mythical land of Prydain during the Early Middle Ages, the film centers on a wicked emperor known as the Horned
King, who hopes to secure an ancient magical cauldron that will aid him in his desire to conquer the world.
He is opposed by young swineherder Taran, the young Princess Eilonwy, the harp-playing bard Fflewddur Fflam, and a friendly
wild creature named Gurgi, who seek to destroy the cauldron to prevent the Horned King from ruling the world.
Disney acquired the film rights to the books in 1973,
with production beginning in 1980.
It was originally scheduled to be released at Christmas 1984, but several scenes, particularly in
the film's climax, were found to be disturbing to children during a test screening.
The newly appointed Walt Disney Studios chairman Jeffrey Katzenberg ordered the
scenes to be cut, which caused its release to be delayed to 1985.
It was the first Disney animated film to receive a PG rating, as well as the
first Disney animated film to feature computer-generated imagery.
The Black Cauldron was released by Buena Vista
Pictures Distribution on July 24, 1985.
The film received mixed reviews from critics.
Being the most expensive animated film ever made at the time, it was a box-office bomb, grossing just $21 million
against a budget of $44 million and putting the future of Disney's animation department in jeopardy.
Because of its commercial failure, Disney did not
release the film on home media until 1997.
It has since gained a cult following.
The film explores themes of witch, based on novel or book, pig, magic, sword.